Guide to the Jeffrey Family Photographic Collection, 1840-1900
Special Collections
Guide to the Jeffrey Family Photographic Collection,
1840-1900
PA46M137
Ross, Jane Charlotte McConnell (?-1869); Jeffrey Family; Jeffrey-Morgan Family
.5 cu. ft. (2 boxes): 76 items
University of Kentucky Special Collections Lexington, Kentucky 40506
Collection is available to researchers by appointment.
Allen, Martha; Confederate States of America. Army. Morgan's Cavalry Division; Hecker, Guy, 1856-1938; Hunt-Morgan Family; Jeffrey Family; Jeffrey, Alexander, 1815-1899; Jeffrey, Alexander Jr., ?-1902; Jeffrey, Charlotte Ross, 1841-1904; Jeffrey, Clarissa Greig, 1854-1892; Jeffrey, John, 1817-1881; Jeffrey, Julia G., 1839-?; Jeffrey, Mary Higham, 1858-1935; Jeffrey, Virginia Abercrombie, 1867-1934; Jeffrey, William, 1812-1867; Lexington Gas Company (Ky.); Morgan Calvin Cogswell III, 1873-1908; Morgan, John Hunt, 1825-1864; Morgan, John Hunt, 1870-1940; Parrish, Henry S.; Pierson, Charles; Porter, Albert Augustus, 1830-1888; Preston, William, 1816-1887; Ross, Jane Charlotte McConnell, ?-1869; Speed, Alice Keats; Vertner, Rosa Griffith (Johnson)(Jeffrey), 1828-1894
The Jeffrey Family of Rochester and Canandaigua, New York, and later of Lexington and Louisville, Kentucky were natives of Scotland who immigrated to America in the 1850s. John Jeffrey (1817-1881) owned and operated John Jeffrey and Co., which built and managed coal gas companies in many southern and midwestern cities and two in Cuba. John Jeffrey eventually settled in Louisville, KY and married Georgiana Augusta Wylie Keats (1798-1879), the widow of George Keats (1797-1841) and the brother of the famed English poet, John Keats (1795-1821).
Working with John was his brother, Alexander Jeffrey (1815-1899), who served as president of the Lexington (Ky.) Gas Company during the latter half of the 19th century. Alexander's first wife, Delia Granger, bore him at least two daughters, Julia G. Jeffrey (1839-?) (married to Albert Augustus Porter (1837-1888)) and Charlotte Ross Jeffrey (1841-1904) (married to Charles Pierson). Both daughters continued to live in Rochester and Canandaigua, New York, as did John and Alexander's brother William Jeffrey (1812-1867) and his children.
Widowed sometime in the 1850s, Alexander met his 2nd wife, Rosa Griffith Vertner (1828-1894), poetess, novelist, and widow of Claudius M. Johnson (?-1861), whom he married in 1862. At the time of their marriage, Rosa had four living children: Dan Vertner Johnson (1848-?), Henry Johnson (1850-?), Rosa Vertner Johnson (1854-), and Claudius M. Johnson Jr. (1852-1919), who served as Lexington mayor from 1880-1889. Claudius Jr. married Anne America Morgan (1865-1915), 2nd cousin of Confederate General John Hunt Morgan.
Rosa and Alexander went on to have at least three children of their own: Alexander Jeffrey Jr. (?-1902), Dunbar Jeffrey (1866-1892) and Virginia Abercrombie Jeffrey (1867-1934). Also living in Lexington with Alexander Sr. at this time was his maternal aunt Jane Charlotte McConnell Ross (?-1869). Alexander Jr. married Martha Allen, daughter of T.N. Allen, who was a friend of Alexander Sr. friend from Olympia, Washington. Virginia Abercrombie married John Hunt Morgan II (1870-1940), nephew of Confederate General John Hunt Morgan.
The Jeffrey Family Photographic Collection, 1840-1900 consists of tintypes, albumen cartes de visite, and gelatin silver prints of the Jeffrey Family of Scotland, Rochester, New York, Louisville and Lexington, Kentucky and a few personal photographs by John Hunt Morgan II (1870-1940), husband of Virginia Abercrombie Jeffrey (1876-1934).
Related Material
The Jeffrey Family Photographic Collection, 1840-1900 consists of tintypes, albumen carte-de-visite, and gelatin silver prints of the Jeffrey Family of Scotland, Rochester, New York, and Louisville and Lexington, Kentucky and a few personal photographs by John Hunt Morgan (II) (1870-1940), husband of Virginia Abercrombie Jeffrey (1876-1934).
Items #45-76 were distributed loose in the Jeffrey Family Papers, 1818-1903 (46M137). Series consists of photographs of Alexander Jeffrey (1815-1899) and other members of the Jeffrey family. The series appears to have been assembled or produced by Virginia Abercrombie Jeffrey (1876-1934) and her husband John Hunt Morgan (II) (1870-1940). Items #67-71 appear to have typed notations on the back by John Hunt Morgan (II).
Stanton, Charles P. Bluegrass pioneers: a chronicle of the Hunt and Morgan families of Lexington, Kentucky including their antecedents and descendants. Brooklyn, NY: C.P. Stanton, 1996.
Jeffrey Family Papers, 1818-1903, 46M137, Special Collections, University of Kentucky Libraries.
John Hunt Morgan II Collection, 1815-1940, MSC 23, Special Collections, Transylvania University, Lexington.
Alexander Jeffrey Papers, 1835-1899, Special Collections, The Filson Historical Society, Louisville, Kentucky
John Jeffrey Papers, 1836-1879, Special Collections, The Filson Historical Society, Louisville, Kentucky
Rosa Vertner Jeffrey Papers, 1855-1892, Special Collections, The Filson Historical Society, Louisville, Kentucky
William Jeffrey Papers, 1852-1876, Special Collections, The Filson Historical Society, Louisville, Kentucky
Container List
- Jane Charlotte McConnell Ross Album
  Items #1-44 were housed in a photographic album identified as belonging to Jane Charlotte McConnell Ross (?-1869), the maternal aunt of Alexander Jeffrey (1815-1899). This series consists of Jeffrey family members, focusing on the Rochester and Canandaigua, New York branches of the family.
  - "J. McConnell my brother" written under image on album page (Caldest, Blanford & Co., London, England), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 1)
  - Unidentified women (Powelson, Rochester, NY), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 2)
  - Commercially produced image entitled "Domestic Life in Turkey / As introduced at the Lectures on Turkey by Mr. Oscanyan."; note in pencil on back: "Dear Father please / accept this for your / book I selected it out / of a set of Turkish / ones because the / Lady looks so like / [illegible], every one is / struck with the / likeness / Bessie (Chas. D. Fredricks & Co.), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 3)
  - Brigadier General William Preston (1816-1887), C.S.A.; Lexington, KY native; in uniform; back of the image notes in ink: "Robert Wickliffe Preston / Havana 4 March 1964 " (C. D. Fredricks and Co., Habana (Havana, Cuba)), 1864; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 4)
  - Charlotte Ross Jeffrey (1st marriage: Pierson) (2nd marriage: Hamilton) (1841-1904) Same image as #12 (Brady, New York, NY and Washington, D.C.), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 5)
  - April Adams (not a firm identification) (unknown), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 6)
  - William Jeffrey (1815-1867) with his two daughters (left to right), Clarissa Greig Jeffrey (1854-1892) and Mary Higham Jeffrey (1858-1935) (unknown), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 7)
  - "Mrs. Willme Junison [?]" written under image on album page (unknown), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 8)
  - "Jeffrey Hill York [?] Rissi [?]" written in pencil along bottom of backing card (Milne, Photographer, Hamilton, C. W.), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 9)
  - "Charles Th[?] Pierson" written under image on album page, Charles Pierson was the husband of Charlotte Ross Jeffrey (Faris, 751 Broadway; tax stamp dated "7 Jan 71"), 1871; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 10)
  - Alexander Jeffrey (1815-1899) (James McPherson, Photographer, Niagara Falls, NY), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 11)
  - Charlotte Ross Jeffrey (1st marriage: Pierson) (2nd marriage: Hamilton) (1841-1904); written in pencil on back: "To dear Aunt Ross / from / Charlotte"; Same image as #5 (Brady, New York, NY and Washington, D.C.), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 12)
  - Agnes Cunningham (not a firm identification); written on back in ink: "To dear Miss Rosa / Nov 25th 1861" (unknown), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 13)
  - Albert Augustus Porter (1838-1888); same image as #21 (James McPherson, Photographer, Niagara Falls, NY), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 14)
  - Charlotte Ross Jeffrey (1st marriage: Pierson) (2nd marriage: Hamilton) (1844-1904) (S. Mason, Niagara Falls, NY), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 15)
  - Julia Jeffrey Porter (1839-?) with unidentified infant; same as #20 (James McPherson, Photographer, Niagara Falls, NY), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 16)
  - Two unidentified children (unknown), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 17)
  - April Adams (not a firm identification) (Brady, New York, NY and Washington, D.C.), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 18)
  - Unidentified woman (Powelson, Rochester, NY), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 19)
  - Julia Jeffrey Porter (1839-?) with unidentified infant; same as #16 (James McPherson, Photographer, Niagara Falls, NY), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 20)
  - Albert Augustus Porter (1838-1888); same as image #14 (James McPherson, Photographer, Niagara Falls, NY), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 21)
  - "April Adams" written under image on album page (J. F. Ryder, Cleveland, OH), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 22)
  - "Miss Beattre [?]" written under image on album page (J. B. Roberts & Co., Rochester, NY), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 23)
  - Unidentified infant (possibly Alexander Jeffrey Jr.); written on the backing card in ink: "For Aunt Ross for Alex." (unknown), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 24)
  - "Mr. Monroe" written under image on album page (Brady, New York, NY), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 25)
  - William McTaggart; written under image on album page: "Wm McTaggart Harrow School" (F. H. Mares, Dublin School of Photography), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 26)
  - "April Adams" written under image on album page (Finley & son, Canadaigua, NY), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 27)
  - "Angus McTaggart / 42 Montague / London" written under image on album page (P. F. Cooper, Philadelphia, PA), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 28)
  - Charlotte Ross Jeffrey (1st marriage: Pierson) (2nd marriage: Hamilton) (1844-1904) (J. Marsden Fox / Menzo E. Gates / Rochester, NY), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 29)
  - Unidentified woman (Levitsky, 22, Rue de Choiseul), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 30)
  - (left to right), Clarissa Greig Jeffrey (1854-1892) and Mary Highham Jeffrey (1858-1935); written on back in pencil: "C+M Jeffrey / Sept. 16 1861" (unknown), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 31)
  - "Henriette Jelf-Sharp 1865" written in ink on back (Window & Bridge; 63 Baker St., London), Albumen Cartes-de-visit (Box 1, Othertype 32)
  - Unidentifed woman (Powelson, Rochester, NY), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 33)
  - Unidentified man (J. H. Kent, Rochester, NY), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 34)
  - Charlotte Ross Jeffrey (1st marriage: Pierson) (2nd marriage: Hamilton) (1844-1904); written on the back in pencil: "C. J. Pierson" (Charlotte Jeffrey Pierson) (W. Kurtz, NY), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 35)
  - "Pointer and Partridge." printed along the bottom of the backing card; commercially produced reproduction of a painting or illustration (New York Photographic Co., New York, NY), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 36)
  - Niagara Falls, NY; written in ink on the back: "For dear Father / on his birthday" (James McPherson, Photographer, Niagara Falls, NY), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 37)
  - Unidentified woman (S. Mason, Niagara Falls, NY), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 38)
  - Unidentified woman (J. T. Upson, Buffalo, NY), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 39)
  - Charles Pierson (J. Marsden Fox / Menzo E. Gates / Rochester, NY), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 40)
  - Unidentified Confederate soldier (Sheldon a& Swymmer, New Orleans, LA), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 41)
  - Unidentified woman (Brady, New York, NY and Washington, D.C.), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 42)
  - Charlotte Ross Jeffrey (1st marriage: Pierson) (2nd marriage: Hamilton) (1844-1904) (Fox & Gates, Rochester, NY), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 43)
  - Unidentified man (unknown), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 44)
- Jeffrey-Morgan Family
  Items #45-76 were loosely distributed within the Jeffrey Family Papers, 1818-1903 (46M137). This series consists of photographs of Alexander Jeffrey (1815-1899) and other members of the Jeffrey family. The series appears to have been assembled or produced by Virginia Abercrombie Jeffrey (1876-1934) and her husband John Hunt Morgan II (1870-1940). Items #67-71 appear to have typed notations on the back by John Hunt Morgan II.
  - Alexander Jeffrey (1815-1899); same image as #11 (James McPherson, Photographer, Niagara Falls, NY), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 45)
  - Alexander Jeffrey (1815-1899) (Johns & Faught, Lexington, KY), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 46)
  - Alexander Jeffrey (1815-1899) (Mullen, Lexington, KY), Albumen Cabinet Card (Box 1, Othertype 47)
  - Alexander Jeffrey (1815-1899) (Jas. Mullen, Lexington, KY), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 48)
  - Unidentified man and woman (unknown), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 49)
  - Two young boys (unknown), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 50)
  - "Mark Metzger" written in pencil on the back (unknown), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 51)
  - Unidentified woman and female child (Twyman, Ramsgate), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 52)
  - Unidentified young girl (Morgan, Paris KY), [n.d.]; Printing-out paper Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 53)
  - Two unidentified young girls and a young boy (unknown), Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 54)
  - Alice Keats Speed (identification by unknown source) (unknown), [n.d.]; Tintype (Box 1, Othertype 55)
  - Four unidentified men (unknown), [n.d.]; Tintype (Box 1, Othertype 56)
  - Unidentified young boy (unknown), [n.d.]; Tintype (Box 1, Othertype 57)
  - Unidentified infant (unknown), [n.d.]; Tintype (Box 1, Othertype 58)
  - Unidentified girl (unknown), [n.d.]; Tintype (Box 1, Othertype 59)
  - Unidentified girl (unknown), [n.d.]; Tintype (Box 1, Othertype 60)
  - Unidentified man (unknown), [n.d.]; Tintype (Box 1, Othertype 61)
  - Two unidentified women (unknown), [n.d.]; Tintype (Box 1, Othertype 62)
  - Unidentified woman; possibly Martha Allen (Jeffrey) (unknown), [n.d.]; Gelatin printing-out paper (Box 1, Othertype 63)
  - Unidentified woman (Dick Cable, Paris KY), Gelatin printing-out paper (Box 1, Othertype 64)
  - Virginia Abercrombie Jeffrey (?-1934) (aka Virginia Jeffrey Morgan); written in ink on back: "Virginia Jeffrey / age 4 years" (James Mullen, Lexington KY), [n.d.]; Albumen (Box 1, Othertype 65)
  - Virginia Abercrombie Jeffrey (?-1934) (aka Virginia Jeffrey Morgan); written in ink on back: "Miss Virginia Abercrombie Jeffrey / 1876" (unknown), [n.d.]; Albumen, hand-painted (Box 1, Othertype 66)
  - Calvin Cogswell Morgan the 3rd; typed on back: "#20. My brother, Calvin Cogswell Morgan 3rd. Sometime in the early 90's, I should say. J H M" (unknown), [n.d.]; Black and white developing-out paper (Box 1, Othertype 67)
  - John Hunt Morgan Jr.; typed on back: "#21. John Hunt Morgan ( 2nd )" (unknown), Black and white developing-out paper (Box 1, Othertype 68)
  - Mike Feeney; typed on back: "# Mike Feeney, for many years, Supt. of the old Lex. Gas Works, on the South side of West Main Dtreet [sic], between Spring and Patterson Streets, on the site now occupied by the [unfinished] #25"; "26" ink on front of image (unknown), Black and white developing-out paper (Box 1, Othertype 69)
  - Martha Allen; typed on back: "Mrs. Alexander Jeffrey Jrl [sic] ( Martha Allen Jeffrey ) on left of group. Others unidentified." (unknown), Black and white developing-out paper (Box 1, Othertype 70)
  - Martha Allen; typed on back: "Mrs. Alexander Jeffrey Jr. ( Martha Allen Jeffrey ) Probably on Cemetary [sic] pond" (unknown), Black and white developing-out paper (Box 1, Othertype 71)
  - Brigadier General John Hunt Morgan (1825-1864) C.S.A.; (aka The Thunderbolt of the Confederacy); leader of the 2nd Kentucky Cavalry; printed along the bottom of the backing card: "Col. John H. Morgan / The Marion of the South" (E. Anthony, New York NY), Albumen Cartes-de-visite, commercially mass-produced (Box 1, Othertype 72)
  - Captain Henry S. Parrish (?-?) U.S.A.; 20th Kentucky Volunteer Infantry, Company A; written in pencil on the back" Yours Truly / H. S. Parrish / Capt Company A 20th Ky.Regt" (unknown), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 73)
  - "Captain Robert Air" written in pencil on back (unknown), [n.d.]; Albumen Cartes-de-visite (Box 1, Othertype 74)
  - Confederate veterans reunion; typed caption: "Georgetown 'Gang' - Aug. 18th 1917 - left to right / Standing: Mike Haggard, Thomas Ewing, Jeff Zeysing, Ely Blackburn / Sitting: John Crumbaugh, Thomas Allen, W. A. Gaines, G. B. Brown, Walter Shropshire, Jas. F. Askew."; handwritten on the back: "From J. C. Zeysing / Georgetown / KY" (unknown), Black and white developing-out paper (Box 1, Othertype 75)
  - Guy Hecker (1856-1938), pitcher and hitter for the Louisville Eclipse, 1882-1890 (unknown), Engraving on card stock (Box 1, Othertype 76)